Ivan C. Karp
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Artists' letters to Ivan and Marilynn Karp
1960-2011
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ivan C. Karp
1.0 linear feet
The Artists' letters to Ivan and Marilynn Karp measure 1.0 linear feet and date from 1960-2011, with the bulk of materials dating from 1976-2000. Ivan Karp founded and operated the OK Harris Gallery in the Soho area of New York City. The letters provide insight into the Karps' manner of working and maintaining relationships with OK Harris artists. The collection includes not only artists' letters but also miscellaneous letters from individuals involved in the New York City world of arts and letters.
Provenance
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 2010 by Marilynn Karp.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Ivan Conrad Karp (b. 1926) founded the OK Harris Gallery in the Soho section of New York City in 1969. His wife, Marilynn Gelfman Karp (b. 1939) is a sculptor, photographer, and professor of art.
Ivan C. Karp is credited with launching the careers of Pop artists such as Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Robert Rauschenberg and Claes Oldenburg. He was co-director of the Leo Castelli Gallery from 1959-1969. The presence of the OK Harris Gallery in Soho helped form the neighborhood's character as a fine arts center. Karp is also the author of Doobie Doo (1966), an early Pop Art novel, as well as a writer on topics of fine art and the art business. Karp also has been actively involved in architectural preservation efforts in New York City. He and Marilynn Gelfman were married in 1953.
Marilynn Gelfman Karp (b.1939) works with mixed media and found objects and is the recipient of an award for sculpture from the American Academy of Arts and Letters. She is the author of In Flagrante Collecto (2006), a book about the avocation of collecting. Both the Karps are avid collectors of fine art and items of material culture, which are of special interest to Mrs. Karp.
Scope and Content Note
The Artists' letters to Ivan and Marilynn Karp measure 1.0 linear feet and date from 1960-2011, with the bulk of materials dating from 1976-2000. Ivan Karp founded and operated the OK Harris Gallery in the Soho area of New York City. The letters provide insight into the Karps' manner of working and maintaining relationships with OK Harris artists. The collection includes not only artists' letters but also miscellaneous letters from individuals involved in the New York City world of arts and letters.The Artists' letters to Ivan and Marilynn Karp measure 1.0 linear feet and date from 1960-2011, with the bulk of materials dating from 1976-2000. Ivan Karp founded and operated the OK Harris Gallery in the Soho area of New York City. The letters provide insight into the Karps' manner of working and maintaining relationships with OK Harris artists. The collection includes not only artists' letters but also miscellaneous letters from individuals involved in the New York City world of arts and letters.
The letters from artists are often illustrated and can include postcards or greeting cards, sometimes made or embellished by the artists. Enclosures consist of photographs, clippings and other printed material. The letters are both personal and professional, often expressing gratitude for the Karps' hospitality or help, or chronicling family news and activities. The letters also mention sales of artwork, exhibitions or commissions or respond to comments Ivan Karp has offered with respect to artwork.
Also included is a folder called "Artist Guest House/Studio Occupants," which amounts to a guest register of forms filled out by artists recording the dates they stayed at the guest house/studio as guests of OK Harris.
The letters are arranged in three series relating to the authors' professions and chronologically within folders. There also are two folders of records of artists' use of the Karp country home guest cottages, which is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Artists' letters, 1960-2011 (Box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Other letters, circa 1976-2000 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Guest House records, 1983-2010 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
Subjects:
O.K. Harris Gallery (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects-Topical:
Art dealers--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Illustrated letters; Photographs
Names:
Karp, Marilynn Gelfman
- Artists' Letters, 1960-2011, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
  Letters from artists consists of many handwritten letters, homemade holiday cards, margin drawings, amusing or interesting postcards, photographs and other materials, all shedding light on the artists' personalities and their relationships with the Karps. The individual folders of letters mostly cover short time periods but a few cover longer periods, giving details of family, and career development and life milestones.
  Other letters discuss financial matters or subjects relating to Karp's critique of artwork submitted to him. Some of the more substantive or lengthy letter collections relate to artists: Deborah Butterfield, John Salt, John Baeder and Robert Ginder. There also is an Artists' Letters A-Z file, which contains only one or two letters, cards or correspondence per artist.
  - Daniel Abraham, undated, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alessandro Algardi, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arman, undated, 1981-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Baeder, 1978-2011 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Roland Baladi, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert Bechtle, undated, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mattie Berhang, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jake Berthot, undated, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Douglas Bond, undated, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Deborah Butterfield, undated, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Don Celender, undated, 1975-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John Clem Clarke and Jane P. Clarke, undated, 1978-2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Davis Cone, undated, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Robert Cottingham, undated, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - John DeAndrea, undated, 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dan Douke, undated, 1985-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Leonard Dufresne, undated, 1984-2010 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Erro, undated, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - John Fawcett, undated, circa 1985-2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - David Furman, undated, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Robert Ginder and Carawood Ginder, undated, 1990-2011 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ralph Goings and Shannah Goings, undated, 1984-2011 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Duane Hanson and Wesla (Liz) Hanson, undated, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Alan Harrison, 1985,1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - John Kacere and Maja Bankava, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Carlo Lamanga and Kathryn Lamanga (Kitty Hollenbeck), undated, 1982-2011 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Jasper Johns" by Mark Lancaster, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Milo Lazarevich, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Marilyn Levine, undated, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Roy Lichenstein and Dorothy Lichenstein, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Richard Lippold, undated, 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Richard McLean, undated, 1977-2010 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Richard Pettibone and Shirley Pettibone, undated, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Edward Roggee, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Robert Rohm, 1997-2010 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - John Salt and Jean Salt, undated, 1973-2010 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Patterson Sims, undated, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - James Van Patten, 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Robert Van Vranken, undated, 1990-2005 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Tom Wesselmann and Claire Wesselmann, undated, 1974-2005 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - James Wines, undated, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Artists' Letters A-Z (One to Two Letters per Artist), undated, 1960-2011 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Other Letters, circa 1976-2000, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  This series contains a small quantity of letters from collectors, other art dealers and museum administrators in addition to a Miscellaneous file, which includes letters from notables such as Truman Capote, Calvin Trillin of The New Yorker magazine and William Grimes of The New York Times.
  - Letters from Collectors, undated, 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letters from Art Dealers, undated, 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Letters from Museum Administrators, undated, 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, undated, 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Guest House records1983-2010, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  The Karps maintain a country house in Charlottesville, New York, where artists stay and work; numerous artists were guest multimple times. This series contains forms printed on the OK Harris letterhead that artists completed and signed, specifying dates they used the guest house and studio.
  - Artist Guest House and Studio Occupants, undated, 1983-2010, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 47-48)